Finding Aid for the Carole Pateman Papers, 1959-2009 LSC.2324
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carole Pateman papers
Bulk, 1960-1980
1959-2009
LSC.2324
UCLA Library Special Collections
4.0 linear feet (9 boxes and 2 half boxes)
Carole Pateman (1940- ) is a Distinguished Professor Emeritus in the UCLA Department of Political Science. She was the first woman President of the International Political Science Association (1991-1994) and was President of the American Political Science Association (2009-2011). Her books include Participation and Democratic Theory (1970), The Problem of Political Obligation (1985), The Sexual Contract (1988), and The Disorder of Women: Democracy, Feminism and Political Theory (1989). The collection consists of materials related to Pateman's career as a scholar and professor, her published works, as well as her collection of publications, clippings, and ephemera from the 1960s and 1970s related to anarchism, socialism, labor organizing, war resistance, and civil disobedience.
Pateman, Carole
Conditions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Carole Pateman; Gift; 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8108418
Biographical/Historical note
Carole Pateman was born in Sussex, England on December 11, 1940. From a working-class family, Pateman benefited from British social reforms of the 1940s which allowed her to attend Oxford University through merit-based examinations, where she earned her BA, MA, and PhD. Pateman was appointed to the Department of Political Science at UCLA in 1990 and taught there until becoming a professor emeritus. Pateman was the first woman President of the International Political Science Association (1991-1994) and President of American Political Science Association (2009-2011). She was awarded honorary doctorates from the Australian National University, the National University of Ireland, and Helsinki University. Her accomplishments include: Fellow of the Australian Academy of Social Sciences (1980), the American Academy for Arts and Sciences (1996), and the British Academy (2007). Pateman is known for her books Participation and Democratic Theory (1970), The Problem of Political Obligation (1985), The Sexual Contract (1988), and The Disorder of Women: Democracy, Feminism and Political Theory (1989).
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of materials related to UCLA political science faculty Carole Pateman, including materials related to her work as a professor and scholar. A highlight is her collection of publications, clippings, and ephemera from the late 1950s through the 1970s related to anarchism, socialism, labor organizing, war resistance, and civil disobedience. The collection also includes materials from courses taught, lectures, published works, and correspondence.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Anarchy publications, 1960-2001
Series 2: Academic work, 1985-2009
Related Material
The Carole Pateman papers, MS.2016.016. Available at Feminist Theory Archive, Brown University Library.
Pateman, Carole--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Political Science--Faculty--Archives.; Anarchism; Communism; Labor; Political scientists--California--Los Angeles--Archives.
- Series 1: Anarchy publications, Bulk, 1960-1975; 1959-2001
  Scope and Contents note
  Series includes fliers, pamphlets, and other ephemera primarily from the late 1950s through the 1970s related to anarchism, socialism, labor organizing, war resistance, and civil disobedience. The materials are mainly from the United Kingdom and United States. Also includes newspaper clippings about these topics, some are attributed to Pateman, some are attributed to other authors, and some are unattributed.
  Organization and Arrangement
  Items are organized by publication title and by subject.
  - Anarchy 1-8, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anarchy 9, 11, 15-20, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anarchy 21-28, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anarchy 29-36, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anarchy 37-44, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anarchy 45-47, 51-53, 55, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anarchy 56-63, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anarchy 64-71, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anarchy 72-79, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anarchy 80-87, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anarchy 88-95, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anarchy 96-101, 103-104, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Anarchy 105-112, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anarchy 113-118, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anarchy Second Series 1-7, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Anarchy Second Series 8-15, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Peace News and Radical Education Project, circa 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CIRA 20-22, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - CIRA 23-25, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Civil disobedience pamphlets, 1960-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Labor pamphlets, 1960-2001 (Box 6, Folder 2, Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Socialism pamphlets, 1960-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - War resistance pamphlets, 1960-2001 (Box 3, Folder 8, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Anarchism pamphlets, 1960-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3, Box 4, Folder 3-7)
  - Inside Story, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bulletin of Anarchist Research, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 9, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity, circa 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Half a Century of Revolutionary Struggle, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - War resistance fliers, circa 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Politics and organizing clippings, 1973-1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - War resistance clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Wildcat 1, 2, 4-10, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Libertarian Teacher, 1967-1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Daily Chronicle clippings, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper articles, circa 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Academic work, 1985-2009
  Series includes Pateman's lecture drafts, transcripts, correspondence, materials for courses taught at UCLA, manuscripts, reviews, and discussions of Pateman's books and articles. Series also includes materials relating to Pateman's involvement in the American Academy of Arts & Sciences (AAAS), the American Political Science Association (APSA), the International Political Science Association (IPSA), and photographs of Pateman's international travels.
  Arrangement note
  Items are organized by event and by publication.
  - Oxford essays and early lectures, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Course syllabi, 1988-2009 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Strange Anarchy by Graham James Baugh, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Lecture drafts and transcripts, circa 1990-2003 (Box 7, Folder 7, Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  - Lecture correspondence and publicity, 1982-1995 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - The Jefferson Memorial Lectures, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The Second York Lecture in Political Science, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The Wesson Lectures in Problems of Democracy, 1992-2000 (Box 9, Folder 5-7)
  - McDonald Constitutional Lecture, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Vilhelm Aubert Memorial Lecture, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sir Douglas Robb Lecture, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, circa 1990-2000 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - The Sexual Contract: correspondence and reviews, 1989-2002 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The Problem of Political Obligation: correspondence and reviews, 1980-1999 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Reviews and discussions of Pateman's work, 1989-1992 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - AAAS and APSA election correspondence, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Genesis, Fathers and Wives, 1980-1983 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - IPSA meeting trips photo album, 1987-1994 (Box 10, Folder 11-12, Box 11, Folder 1-3)